<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc
[
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="no"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>

<rfc ipr="pre5378Trust200902" category="std" submissionType="IETF" consensus="true"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" docName="draft-yn-netmod-yang-xml-latest">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="XML Encoding of YANG Data">XML Encoding of Data Modeled with YANG</title>
        <author initials="K" surname="Watsen" fullname='Kent Watsen' role="editor">
            <organization>Watsen Networks</organization>
            <address>
                <email>kent+ietf@watsen.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date/>
        <area>Operations</area>
        <workgroup>NETMOD Working Group</workgroup>
        <keyword>yang</keyword>
        <keyword>xml</keyword>
        <abstract>
            <t>This document defines encoding rules for representing YANG modeled
            configuration data, state data, parameters of Remote Procedure Call (RPC)
            operations or actions, and notifications defined using XML.</t>
        </abstract>
        <note title="GitHub Information (to be removed by RFC Editor)">
            <t>This document is developed on GitHub (<eref target="https://github.com/netmod-wg/yang2-and-friends"/>).
            If you wish to contribute, please consider opening a pull request (PR).  Please see the
            README file for details.</t>
        </note>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction">
            <t>This document defines encoding rules for representing YANG
            <xref target="RFC7950"/> modeled configuration
            data, state data, parameters of Remote Procedure Call (RPC)
            operations or actions, and notifications defined using
            the Extensible Markup Language (XML) <xref target="XML"/>.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Terminology and Notation">
            <!-- copy/paste/edit from RFC 7951 -->

            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
            "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
            and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
            in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
            when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
            <t>The following terms are defined in <xref target="RFC7950"/>:</t>
            <ul spacing="compact">
                <li>action</li>
                <li>anydata</li>
                <li>anyxml</li>
                <li>augment</li>
                <li>container</li>
                <li>data node</li>
                <li>data tree</li>
                <li>identity</li>
                <li>instance identifier</li>
                <li>leaf</li>
                <li>leaf-list</li>
                <li>list</li>
                <li>module</li>
                <li>RPC operation</li>
                <li>submodule</li>
            </ul>
            <t>The following terms are defined in <xref target="RFC6241"/></t>
            <ul spacing="compact">
              <li>configuration data</li>
              <li>notification</li>
              <li>state data</li>
            </ul>
        </section>

        <section title="Properties of the XML Encoding">
            <!-- copy/paste/edit from RFC 7951 -->

            <t>This document defines XML encoding for YANG data trees and their
            subtrees.  It is always assumed that there may be one or more top-level
            elements in XML-encoded configuration data and state data. RPC operations
            and notifications contain a single top-level element.</t>

            <t>Instances of YANG data nodes (leafs, containers, leaf-lists, lists,
            anydata nodes, and anyxml nodes) are encoded as XML elements having
            the name of the YANG data node.  <xref target="names"/>) defines
            how the name is qualified with a namespace, and the following sections
            deal with the value part.  The encoding rules are identical for all
            types of data trees, i.e., configuration data, state data, parameters
            of RPC operations, actions, and notifications.</t>

            <t>With the exception of "anydata" encoding (<xref target="anydata"/>), all rules in
            this document are also applicable to YANG&nbsp;1.0 <xref target="RFC6020"/>.</t>

            <t>With the exception of anyxml and schema-less anydata nodes, it is
            possible to map an XML-encoded data tree to other encodings, such as
            the JSON encoding as defined in <xref target="RFC7951"/>, and vice
            versa.  However, such conversions require the YANG data model to be
            available.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Names and Namespaces" anchor="names">
            <!-- copy/paste/edit from RFC 7951 -->

            <t>An XML element name is always identical to the identifier of the
            corresponding YANG data node.</t>

            <t>All XML elements encoding YANG data are namespace qualified.  The
            XML default namespace is never used in YANG encoded data.</t>

            <t>The namespace of an XML element is either inherited from its ancestor
            or set using the "xmlns" attribute in the element.</t>

            <t>The "xmlns" attribute may either set the XML default namespace or
            define a prefix for the namespace.  Note that the same XML may be
            encoded differently by different implementations.  For instance,
            the following two XML documents are the same.</t>

            <t>Document 1:</t>
            <figure>
                <artwork>
<![CDATA[
<foo xmlns="https://example.com/foo"/>
]]>
                </artwork>
            </figure>

            <t>Document 2:</t>
            <figure>
                <artwork>
<![CDATA[
<my-prefix:foo xmlns:my-prefix="https://example.com/foo"/>
]]>
                </artwork>
            </figure>

            <t>The "namespace" statement of a module determines the namespace
            of all data node names defined in that module.  If a data node is
            defined in a submodule, then the namespace of the main module is used.</t>

            <t>A namespace MUST be set for all top-level XML elements and then
            also whenever the namespaces of the data node and its parent node
            are different.</t>

            <t>For example, consider the following YANG module:</t>

            <figure>
                <artwork>
<![CDATA[
module example-foomod {

  namespace "https://example.com/foomod";

  prefix "foomod";

  container top {
    leaf foo {
      type uint8;
    }
  }
}
]]>
                </artwork>
            </figure>

            <t>If the data model consists only of this module, then the following is
            valid XML-encoded configuration data:</t>

            <figure>
                <artwork>
<![CDATA[
<top xmlns="https://example.com/foomod">
  <foo>54</foo>
</top>
]]>
                </artwork>
            </figure>

            <t>Note that the top-level element sets the default namespace which
            "foo" leaf inherits its parent container "top".</t>

            <t>Now, assume that the container "top" is augmented from another
            module, "example-barmod":</t>

            <figure>
                <artwork>
<![CDATA[
module example-barmod {

  namespace "https://example.com/barmod";

  prefix "barmod";

  import example-foomod {
    prefix "foomod";
  }

  augment "/foomod:top" {
    leaf bar {
      type boolean;
    }
  }
}
]]>
                </artwork>
            </figure>

            <t>Valid XML-encoded configuration data containing both leafs may then
            look like this:</t>
            <figure>
                <artwork>
<![CDATA[
<top xmlns="https://example.com/foomod">
  <foo>54</foo>
  <bar xmlns="https://example.com/barmod">true</bar>
</top>
]]>
                </artwork>
            </figure>

            <t>The "bar" leaf's element sets a new default namespace
            because its parent is defined in a different module.</t>

            <t>Explicit namespace prefixes are sometimes needed when encoding
            values of the "identityref" and "instance-identifier" types.  See
            <xref target="identityref"/> and <xref target="instance-identifier"/>
            for details.</t>

            <t>To improve readability of XML, a client or server
            that generates XML or XPath that uses prefixes SHOULD use the prefix
            defined by the module as the XML namespace prefix, unless there is a
            conflict.</t>

        </section>

        <section title="Encoding of YANG Data Node Instances">

            <section title='The "leaf" Data Node' anchor="leaf">
                <!-- this part from RFC 7950 Section 7.6.6 (XML Encoding Rules) -->
                <t>A leaf node is encoded as an XML element.  The element's local name
                is the leaf's identifier, and its namespace is the module's XML
                namespace (see <xref target="names"/>).</t>
                <t>The value of the leaf node is encoded to XML according to the
                type (see <xref target="types"/> for type encoding rules) and is
                sent as character data in the element.</t>

                <!-- copy/paste/edit from RFC 7951 Section 5.1 (The "leaf" Data Node) -->
                <t>Example: For the leaf node definition</t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork>
<![CDATA[
leaf foo {
  type uint8;
}
]]>
                    </artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>the following is a valid XML-encoded instance:</t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork>
<![CDATA[
<foo>123</foo>
]]>
                    </artwork>
                </figure>
            </section>

            <section title='The "container" Data Node'>
                <!-- this part from RFC 7950 Section 7.5.7 (XML Encoding Rules) -->
                <t>A container node is encoded as an XML element. The element's local name is
                the container's identifier, and its namespace is the module's XML namespace
                (see <xref target="names"/>).</t>
                <t>The container's child nodes are encoded as subelements to the container
                element. If the container defines RPC or action input or output parameters,
                these subelements are encoded in the same order as they are defined within the
                "container" statement. Otherwise, the subelements are encoded in any
                order.</t>
                <t>Any whitespace between the subelements to the container is insignificant,
                i.e., an implementation MAY insert whitespace characters between
                subelements.</t>
                <t>If a non-presence container does not have any child nodes, the container
                may or may not be present in the XML encoding.</t>

                <!-- copy/paste/edit from RFC 7951 Section 5.2 (The "container" Data Node) -->
                <t>Example: For the container definition</t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork>
<![CDATA[
container bar {
  leaf foo {
    type uint8;
  }
}
]]>
                    </artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>the following is valid XML-encoded instance data:</t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork>
<![CDATA[
<bar>
    <foo>123</foo>
</bar>
]]>
                    </artwork>
                </figure>
            </section>

            <section title='The "leaf-list" Data Node'>
                <!-- this part from RFC 7950 Section 7.7.8 (XML Encoding Rules) -->
                <t>A leaf-list node is encoded as a series of XML elements. Each element's
                local name is the leaf-list's identifier, and its namespace is the module's
                XML namespace (see <xref target="names"/>).  There is no XML element
                surrounding the leaf-list as a whole.</t>
                <t>The value of each leaf-list entry is encoded to XML according to the type
                and is sent as character data in the element (see <xref target="types"/> for
                type encoding rules).</t>
                <t>The XML elements representing leaf-list entries MUST appear in the order
                specified by the user if the leaf-list is "ordered-by user"; otherwise, the
                order is implementation dependent. The XML elements representing leaf-list
                entries MAY be interleaved with elements for siblings of the leaf-list, unless
                the leaf-list defines RPC or action input or output parameters.</t>

                <!-- copy/paste/edit from RFC 7951 Section 5.3 (The "leaf-list" Data Node) -->
                <t>Example: For the leaf-list definition</t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork>
<![CDATA[
leaf-list foo {
  type uint8;
}
]]>
                    </artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>the following is a valid XML-encoded instance:</t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork>
<![CDATA[
<foo>123</foo>
<foo>0</foo>
]]>
                    </artwork>
                </figure>
            </section>

            <section title='The "list" Data Node'>
                <!-- this part from RFC 7950 Section 7.8.5 (XML Encoding Rules) -->
                <t>A list is encoded as a series of XML elements, one for each entry in the
                list. Each element's local name is the list's identifier, and its namespace is
                the module's XML namespace (see <xref target="names"/>).  There is no XML
                element surrounding the list as a whole.</t>
                <t>The list's key nodes are encoded as subelements to the list's identifier
                element, in the same order as they are defined within the "key" statement.</t>
                <t>The rest of the list's child nodes are encoded as subelements to the list
                element, after the keys. If the list defines RPC or action input or output
                parameters, the subelements are encoded in the same order as they are defined
                within the "list" statement. Otherwise, the subelements are encoded in any
                order.</t>
                <t>Any whitespace between the subelements to the list entry is insignificant,
                i.e., an implementation MAY insert whitespace characters between
                subelements.</t>
                <t>The XML elements representing list entries MUST appear in the order
                specified by the user if the list is "ordered-by user"; otherwise, the order
                is implementation dependent. The XML elements representing list entries MAY be
                interleaved with elements for siblings of the list, unless the list defines
                RPC or action input or output parameters.</t>

                <!-- copy/paste/edit from RFC 7951 Section 5.4 (The "list" Data Node) -->
                <t>Example: For the list definition</t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork>
<![CDATA[
  list bar {
    key foo;
    leaf foo {
      type uint8;
    }
    leaf baz {
      type string;
    }
  }
]]>
                    </artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>the following is a valid XML-encoded instance:</t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork>
<![CDATA[
<bar>
    <foo>123</foo>
    <baz>zig</baz>
</bar>
<bar>
    <foo>456</foo>
    <baz>zag</baz>
</bar>
]]>
                    </artwork>
                </figure>
            </section>

            <section title='The "anydata" Data Node' anchor="anydata">
                <!-- this part from RFC 7950 Section 7.10 (XML Encoding Rules, for anydata) -->
                <t>An anydata node is encoded as an XML element. The element's local name is
                the anydata's identifier, and its namespace is the module's XML namespace (see
                <xref target="names"/>). The value of the anydata node is a set of nodes,
                which are encoded as XML subelements to the anydata element.</t>

                <!-- copy/paste/edit from RFC 7951 Section 5.5 (The "anydata" Data Node) -->
                <t>The anydata data node serves as a container for an arbitrary set of
                nodes that otherwise appear as normal YANG-modeled data.  A data
                model for anydata content may or may not be known at runtime.  In the
                latter case, converting XML-encoded instances to other encodings, such
                as JSON <xref target="RFC7951"/> may be impossible.</t>

                <!-- this part from RFC 7950 Section 7.11.2 (XML Encoding Rules, for anyxml) -->
                <t>Note that any XML prefixes used in the encoding are local to each
                instance encoding.  This means that the same XML may be encoded differently
                by different implementations.</t>

                <!-- copy/paste/edit from RFC 7951 Section 5.5 (The "anydata" Data Node) -->
                <t>Example: For the anydata definition</t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork>
<![CDATA[
anydata data;
]]>
                    </artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>the following is a valid XML-encoded instance:</t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork>
<![CDATA[
<data>
    <notification xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netmod:notification">
        <eventTime>2014-07-29T13:43:01Z</eventTime>
        <event xmlns="https://example.com/example-event">
            <event-class>fault</event-class>
            <reporting-entity>
                <card>Ethernet0</card>
            </reporting-entity>
            <severity>major</severity>
        </event>
    </notification>
</data>
]]>
                    </artwork>
                </figure>
            </section>

            <section title='The "anyxml" Data Node'>
                <t>An anyxml node is encoded the same as an anydata node.  Please see
                <xref target="anydata"/> for how the anydata node is encoded.</t>
            </section>

            <section title="Metadata Objects">
                <t>Apart from instances of YANG data nodes, XML elements MAY contain
                XML attributes for special purposes, such as encoding metadata
                <xref target="RFC7952"/>. The exact syntax and semantics of such
                members are outside the scope of this document.</t>
            </section>

        </section>

        <section title="Representing YANG Data Types in XML Values" anchor="types">

            <t>The type of the XML value in an instance of the leaf or leaf-list
            data node depends on the type of that data node, as specified in the
            following subsections.</t>

            <section title="Numeric Types">
            </section>

            <section title='The "string" Type'>
            </section>

            <section title='The "boolean" Type'>
            </section>

            <section title='The "enumeration" Type'>
            </section>

            <section title='The "bits" Type'>
            </section>

            <section title='The "binary" Type'>
            </section>

            <section title='The "leafref" Type'>
            </section>

            <section title='The "identityref" Type' anchor="identityref">
            </section>

            <section title='The "empty" Type'>
            </section>

            <section title='The "union" Type'>
            </section>

            <section title='The "instance-identifier" Type' anchor="instance-identifier">
            </section>

        </section>

        <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
        </section>
        <section title="Security Considerations">
        </section>

    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
            <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
            <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7950.xml"/>
            <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
            <reference anchor="XML" target="https://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-xml-20081126/">
                <front>
                    <title>Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0 (Fifth Edition)</title>
                    <author fullname="Tim Bray" surname="Bray" initials="T."/>
                    <author fullname="Jean Paoli" surname="Paoli" initials="J."/>
                    <author fullname="Michael Sperberg-McQueen" surname="Sperberg-McQueen"
                         initials="C."/>
                    <author fullname="Eve Maler" surname="Maler" initials="E."/>
                    <author fullname="Francois Yergeau" surname="Yergeau" initials="F."/>
                    <date year="2008" month="November" day="26"/>
                </front><seriesInfo name="W3C Recommendation" value="REC-xml-20081126"/>
            </reference>
        </references>
        <references title="Informative References">
            <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6020.xml"/>
            <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6241.xml"/>
            <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7951.xml"/>
            <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7952.xml"/>
        </references>
        <section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
            <t>Substantial amounts of text in this document was copied from <xref target="RFC7950"/>
            and <xref target="RFC7951"/>.  The authors wish to thank Martin Björklund and
            Ladislav Lhotka for authoring RFC 7950 and RFC 7951, respectively.</t>
        </section>
    </back>
</rfc>
